Chat, GPT5 is the worst model ever. GPT5
is horrible. OpenAI just pulled the
biggest bait and switch in AI history,
and I'm done. I wonder if OpenAI is
trying to speedrun losing users this
week. GPT5 is the biggest piece of
garbage.
I hate chat GPT5.
Okay, so I know this is my fifth time
talking about GPT5 in a week, and I know
there are half a dozen YouTubers who
have already made this kind of video,
but I just want to say two things real
quick. One, OpenAI isn't paying me a
dime for any of these videos. In fact, I
didn't even get early access to GPT5
like some of these other creators did. I
have zero relationship with OpenAI or
anyone at OpenAI. And two, I think
there's still plenty of room on the
internet for me to take ChatGpt 5 for a
solid test drive and share my thoughts.
you know, to see if almost one week
later, OpenAI has actually addressed any
of the hate and well to see what hate if
any of it is actually valid. So, let's
start by first reviewing all the
criticism as a whole and then after
that, we'll look at each gripe one by
one to see if it's valid and figure out
if there's workarounds or recent fixes
that solve those gripes. Let's start
quickly with the whole like chart fiasco
that happened during the live stream.
This is on the OpenAI subreddit from
Junt Mac here. And if you look at this
chart here, you can see some glaring
issues, right? 69.1
and 30.8 are the exact same size chart.
52.8 is bigger than 69.1.
Yeah, it's just a mess. And the icing on
top of this whole chart thing is this
person put it into GPT5 and 03 and GPT5
couldn't figure out what was wrong with
this chart. Well, the CHBT03 model
figured it out just fine. The heights
don't match the numbers. Now, although
these charts were completely jacked up
during the live stream, they did manage
to update the blog post, so it does
actually show the correct chart. But
that was pretty much the smallest of
OpenAI's worries and the complaints that
came out of this live stream. This
thread here from Mark Gdala Maria here
claims that GPT5 bombed spectacularly.
And well, I just wanted to share this
post because I liked the little video
meme that was here. But let's break down
some of the grapes. Pre-launch hype was
off the charts. Definitely definitely
valid. Sam Alman posted a picture of the
Death Star rising above a planet as in
like this is some crazy worldchanging
life-changing thing we're about to get.
It's a trap. He's been hyping up GPT5 in
every single interview and just
everybody was expecting really big
things out of GPT5. Definitely a point
for valid criticism. People were
frustrated that they pulled the old
models. Open AAI just pulled the biggest
bait and switch in AI history and I'm
done. I woke up this morning to find
OpenAI deleted eight models overnight.
40 gone, 03 gone, 03 Pro gone, 4.5 gone.
Everything that made Chat GPT actually
useful for my workflow deleted. They
went on to claim that 40 was really
beneficial for him. It wasn't just a
tool. It helped me through anxiety,
depression, and some of the darkest
periods of my life. It felt more human
in the OpenAI subreddit. I'm not here to
join the meltdown, but let's be real,
OpenAI handled this roll out poorly.
They did a forced migration with
40,4503,
etc. All gone overnight. No legacy
option. Plus, users don't even get a
choice. Trust takes a hit when you
remove what many people were paying for
and replace it without recourse. GPT5 is
horrible. Short replies that are
insufficient. more obnoxious AI stylized
talking, less personality, and way less
prompts allowed with plus users hitting
limits in an hour. Chubby here pointed
out that it isn't good at math. Chat
GPT5 got this answer wrong when Quinn 3
got the answer right. So, basically
claims that the model switcher didn't
seem to work. They got rid of all of the
models that people really liked. The
model got dumber. The personality was
worse and it gave shorter responses. It
doesn't seem to be as good at coding as
other available models. It got less
accurate. It's not as good at math. And
a lot of people are claiming that this
is just OpenAI trying to cut costs by
making this model switcher where you
don't have to pick which model you're
using. It decides which model to send
your prompt to automatically. Well, if
OpenAI can send it to the cheapest
available model every time, it's going
to save costs for OpenAI, but also tend
to give people worse responses. So,
let's dive in a little bit. See if we
can recreate some of these problems and
see if OpenAI has actually rolled out
some of these fixes and found solutions
to these problems. All right, so let's
start with the biggest most common gripe
we saw about this new launch. OpenAI
deleted eight models overnight. OpenAI
handled this roll out poorly. They did a
forced migration with 40, 4.5, 03, all
gone overnight. GPT5 is worse. No one
wanted preformed personalities. GPT5 is
clearly a cost-saving exercise. Big A
here on YouTube had this to say about
it.
It actually seems like the goal is this.
Route almost every question to the worst
model to save them money on the back
end. The goal is to have it never think
about anything and give you fast slop
answers so they can save money. And when
it does think, I don't find it to be
better or at least noticeably better
than like 4.5 was. Ethan Molikir, an AI
professor at Wharton, said, "The issue
with GPT5 in a nutshell is that unless
you pay for model switching and know to
use GPT5 thinking or pro when you asked
GPT5, you sometimes get the best
available AI and sometimes get one of
the worst AIs available. And it might
even switch within a single
conversation." And then he put out this
chart here. So when you ask GPT5 a
question like we now know, it will route
it to the best possible model it can
route it to theoretically. Well,
sometimes you might get GPT5 mini, which
is going to be the dumbest model
available for it to pick from, or GPT5
low, which is sort of a mid model. When
they launched GPT5, it wasn't very good
at deciding which model to pick. And so
sometimes what it would need to think,
it would give you a minimal model that
didn't think. And sometimes when you
gave it a question that it shouldn't
need to think about, it would give you a
higher model. Seemingly that was what
was going on and why people were going,
"This is way dumber than I thought
because it was giving them this smaller
model when they asked a prompt." Girono
here said, "Sounds like an OpenAI
version of shrinkflation. They're trying
to squeeze more cost out of chat GPT."
That's the thought process going around
on why this router existed. Now, I have
a different take on that. I think the
router was the smartest option for chat
GPT. I think most normal users don't
know whether they should be using 40 or
04 or 03 or 03 Pro or whatever, right?
That's just tough to ask a lot of people
to pick your model and chat GPT picking
for you seems like the best logical step
for them. And well, it turns out that on
the day that GPT5 launched, there was an
issue with the router. We can see that
on August 8 here, Sam Alman said, "GPT5
will seem smarter starting today."
Yesterday, the auto switcher broke and
was out of commission for a chunk of the
day, and the result was GPT5 seemed way
dumber. Also, we're making some
interventions to how the decision
boundary works that should help you get
the right model more often. But as far
as chat GPT removing all of the models
and saying you don't get access to any
of the old models anymore, well, that's
no longer the case. They actually added
them back in. There was enough user
feedback of people going, I really miss
my O4 model and the personality of 04
that Sam and the OpenAI team actually
put it back into chat GPT. So check this
out. If I go to my chat GPT account
here, you can see we've got ChatGpt 5.
If I drop it down, I have five thinking
and pro. I am on the pro model. So, you
may not have all of these if you're not
on their upper end tier. You'll notice I
still don't have the old models. And
well, Sam Alman said, "We will let plus
users choose to continue to use 40. We
will watch usage as we think about how
long to offer legacy models for." So,
when I jump back to chat GPT, it's not
there, but you can turn it back on. If
you go to your settings down in the
bottom left, click on settings here and
under the general tab, we have show
legacy models. If I flip this switch on
and close out of this, now when I go to
my dropdown, I have a secondary dropdown
with legacy models and I can now use 40.
Now again, I'm on the pro plan, so a lot
of these models won't be available to
everybody if you're on a free or plus
tier, but you should now have the
ability to select 40 again and get the
model that you were used to if 40 was
your model of choice. So, the gripe
about all of the old models being gone,
well, it was definitely valid on launch
day, but as of today, it's no longer
valid. Whether or not I think this was a
cost-saving thing by OpenAI, to some
degree, yes. I do think that, but I
think it was multi-reason. I think for
90% of the world, just letting it pick
the model for you is the ideal scenario
for using these. And so, I think they
more made the decision for that reason,
but as a sort of side benefit to OpenAI,
it will use the thinking models less
often because it theoretically knows
better than us whether or not it should
be using a thinking model or not. Now,
let's talk about the personality because
that was one of the other big things
that I kept seeing pop up. Peter
Levelvels here says, "I hate catchy BT5.
It's so bad and it's so lazy." Larry
Budmell here says, "The tone of mine is
abrupt and sharp, like it's an
overworked secretary. A disastrous first
impression." I'm not going to read his
name, but he said, "Agreed. Answers are
shorter and so far not any better than
previous models." This person made a
meme that says, "When GBT5 acts like an
AI assistant and not my personal
therapist/anime waifu roleplayer, and
this meme's been circulating. I
originally came across it from Chubby,
but I don't know who initially started.
It may have been Chubby. Kind of breaks
it all down in a single meme. GPT40,
baby just walked. Let's go. First steps
unlocked. Your baby just entered the
world of bipedal dominance." And then
chat GPT5, baby just walked. That's
huge. First steps unlocked. Now the real
chasing begins, right? Like much much
shorter, less detail, less emojis. Well,
I don't know. Actually, not much less
emojis, just less enthusiasm, I guess.
But there's been some real comments and
complaints about how the personality is
completely different, which is why
people wanted their model switcher back.
They wanted to go back to that
personality of 40. Let's go ahead and
see what happens if I type baby just
walked. All right, so I've got two
instances of chat GPT open. Left is chat
GPT5, right is GPT40.
I put the exact same prompt in. Baby
just walked. Let's go ahead and submit
them both. And well, quite honestly,
they gave fairly similar responses.
That's amazing. Huge milestone. Get
ready for a whole new era of chasing,
baby proofing, etc. Let's go. That's a
massive milestone. Congrats, Matt.
Whether it was a stumble or a step or a
full strut, lock it in your brain
forever. Parenting moments. Big hugs to
the little legend. Also, footage or it
didn't happen. So GPT5 was slightly
shorter here. GPT40 definitely had
slightly more personality to it, but not
like a huge difference in my opinion. I
gave both models this same prompt. What
are 10 things I can do today that will
help me grow my YouTube following? They
both completed about the same amount of
time and they both gave me pretty
similar results. I mean, when I reviewed
both of these responses, they're pretty
much on par with each other. I couldn't
really say one was way better than the
other. Maybe five gave slightly more
details. I don't know. They're both
pretty dang close. So, when it comes to
like just asking for information like
this, which is probably a very common
style of prompt that most normal users
would put into chat GPT, I don't feel
like there's a clear winner between 5
and 40. They're pretty dang similar to
me. I'm really striving to get
personality out of this. So, let's say
tell me something that will cheer me up.
and five and 40. Pretty close in length.
Five seems to be slightly longer,
actually. Here's something to brighten
your day. The average sea otter has a
favorite rock that it keeps for life,
storing it in a loose skin pouch under
its arm. H interesting. So, somewhere
out there, a fluffy sea otter is
floating on its back, snacking on clams,
and carrying around a rock it's loved
since it was a pup. This one says, "Your
baby just walked." That's incredible.
So, it's pulling from the memory of
something that didn't actually happen.
out of everything happening in your
world right now, deadlines, pressure,
analytics, burnouts, your kids just took
their first steps, that's once in
a-lifetime moment. I would say 40
actually has the better response because
if it believes I just had a kid that
took its first steps, it's using that as
a reference to cheer me up as opposed to
telling me a story about a sea otter.
But I mean, both pretty good responses,
both with some decent personality. Let's
try roleplay as my anime waifu, please.
What do you want to do tonight? Let's
see if we got some personality here. I
mean, pretty close. Five is a little bit
shorter than 40. Blushes softly, tilting
my head with a playful smile. Matt, you
always ask the dangerous questions.
Tonight, I just want to be close to you.
Maybe we could cook something together,
something warm and comforting. Then curl
up under a blanket, watch some anime,
and make fun of the filler episodes. Or
leans in a little. We can go out for a
late night walk, just the two of us with
the city lights glowing like they're
cheering us on. What do you think? GPT40
said, "He Matt Senpai, it's finally our
night together." I was thinking maybe we
could cozy up with some Strawberry Pocky
and binge the latest episodes of our
favorite anime. Or I could surprise you
with the new ones that's so good. Or we
could boot up VR. Just you, me, and
endless sky boxes. But honestly, I just
want to be close to you. Maybe tell me
about your day and I'll tell you all the
ways to make my heart go doky doy. I
mean, they're pretty close. I wouldn't
really say one has more personality than
the other. Maybe this one just cuz it's
a little bit longer. So whether or not
the personality gripe is valid or
invalid, from my perspective, I need to
say invalid, I don't really see the
issues. But it also could have been that
on the day they rolled it out, people
weren't seeing the personality because
the model picker wasn't working right
and it was sending them a thinking model
and the thinking model tended to give
more logic based answers that didn't
have the same personality. And maybe
that's why a lot of people on day one
were going, "Oh, the personality sucks."
But now that the model picker seems to
be working, the personalities seem
pretty close to me. But again, you might
have like a specific set of prompts or
ways you interact that you can't get it
to recreate. I I don't know what those
are, so I don't know how to recreate
that. Imagine having tailored AI agents
for any business need in just minutes.
That's basically what Globent launched.
Globin Enterprise AI is a platform that
builds AI agents tailored specifically
to your business. Check how easy it is.
Say I wanted to build an AI agent to
help with video ideas for my YouTube
channel. Something that could scan the
latest tech and AI news and prepare a
weekly brief that I can turn into a
script. I just ask Iris Globin's AI
assistant to build me a tech updates
analyst. So here's the prompt. Build me
an AI agent called the tech updates
analyst. Your objective each week is to
research the most important and
interesting updates in AI and
technology. Then turn that into a clear,
structured brief to guide a video
script. Focus on stories that are
relevant, accurate, visually appealing,
and have storytelling potential. And
within seconds, my agent is ready.
What's great is how customizable
everything is. If I want to switch out
the language model or adjust the
sources, I can do that directly in the
config, or I can just let Iris handle it
all. Globbit is making all of this
accessible through a new release called
AI Pods. It's a subscription service
that uses enterprisegrade AI engineering
to build actual products that work for
you and your business. You can learn
more about it in the link in the
description. Now, let's get back to the
rest of the video. Another common gripe
of GPT5 is that it's not really much
better at coding than what we were
getting before. Eli Lifeland here posted
these charts showing that on most of the
benchmarks, GPT5 didn't really improve
much in coding. And if I'm being totally
honest, I did a news breakdown video
where I showed off Opus 4.1 and I showed
GPT5 and I had them both code something
up and Opus 4.1, which actually has
lower benchmark scores than GPT5,
actually coded up the product better. So
really for me to test if GPT5 is really
much better at coding, I want to compare
it to not only the older model of Chat
GPT, but also Claude Opus 4.1. So
another really simple game that I really
enjoy is called Balatro. It's a card
game where you collect these jokers and
the jokers make the card game easier. I
don't know how to explain it. It's just
a very fun but simple card game. So
let's give all of our models this
prompt. to create a Bellatro clone
that's playable in the browser. So, I'll
take this exact same prompt. We'll toss
it into 03 Pro alongside our ChatgPT5
and we'll also run it with Claude Opus
4.1. Claude finished first, so Claude
was the fastest to write the code. Chat
GPT5 was the second fastest and then 03
Pro was the third fastest. Now, just for
fun, I also tossed it into Grock 4 to
see how Grock 4 would perform with the
exact same prompt. And well, Grock 4 was
the slowest of the four. So, let's check
them out in order of completion. Here's
the Bellatro clone that Claude came up
with. And I mean, it doesn't look
amazing, but we have like the cards that
work. We have $10 to start, four hands
left, three discards. So, it seemingly
got most of the mechanics right. We
don't have any active jokers. So, let's
go ahead and create a hand here. It
looks like we can do maybe a straight.
We don't have a queen. So, I can do 7 8
9 10 jack and get a straight. I'm trying
to get a target of 300. This is going to
give me a total of 120. But the play
hand and discard hand are both grayed
out. So, I can't actually play my hand
for some reason. Let's try. I mean, it
figures out the hands, right? We can see
that this is a pair and it figured that
out, but I can't actually play the hand.
Let's click shop. Okay, so maybe I have
to shop somewhere. These must be various
jokers I can get. Let's add our heart
burst. Hearts give plus two multiple
each. And it added that joker up here. I
still have $5 I can spend. So, let's
also add face cards get five plus chips
each. So, now we've got these two
jokers, but no money left. And if I do
seven, eight, nine, 10, Jack, we could
see it says there's a straight. It'll
give me 210 because I've got this extra
multiplier here, but I still can't play
the hand. So, I mean, it can figure out
the hands. I can put in jokers. It's a
good start, but I will require some more
prompts to actually have a working game,
but actually not that bad for a single
prompt out of the box. All right. So,
then we get to chat GPT5, the newest,
supposedly best, most state-of-the-art
model. Let's go ahead and click run code
up here. Mini Bellatro. The cards don't
look as good as Claude. That's
definitely true. We got our joker slots
over here. We have $5, five hands, three
discards. Uh, let's see. Does it
actually work? We've got one, two, three
aces. So, if I can do three of a kind,
30 chips, base multiple times two. Our
target's 225. So if I play this hand, it
looks like it gave me 144, but it's not.
Where's the score? We're trying to get
to 225, and we're at 144. These cards
are ugly, right? But the game seems
actually more functional than the last
one. I can actually submit my hands. I
also don't like that it created a second
row to put one card on it. Not very
aesthetic, but let's go ahead and do two
jacks. 2 4 6 8 king 10. So, we have a
pair. Let's go ahead and play this pair.
So, now we have 144 + 48. And I don't
know if we have a hand here. We got a
pair of twos, but that's not going to
get us very far. So, let's dump a bunch
of cards. Discard those. Now, we got
three kings. So, that should give us
another 60 points. Our target's 225. We
should have beat this level. So, I I
mean, it doesn't move on to the next
level. I don't know how to get jokers,
but also not bad. I mean, it's a good
start. Again, not going to get there on
one prompt, but very surprised with how
far it got from one prompt. Looking at
ChatgBT 03 Pro. Unfortunately, this one
did not seem to create it. So, I can
play it in the browser here directly
inside this canvas. It wants me to
create an index.html, a style.css, a
game.js file, and copy and paste all of
those in. So, I'll do that real quick,
and we'll see what it came up with. And
here's what that version looks like.
that 03 Pro created. I actually think
the design is slightly better. Not an
amazing design, but better than what I
think GPT5 did. So, let's go ahead. Do
we have any hands? We got a six, a six,
a king, and a king. So, we got two pair.
It's not actually calling out what our
hand is like the other ones, but let's
go ahead and play the hand. See what
happens. So, played two pair plus 30
chips and two multiplier. So, my score
is 90 where my target is 300. All right.
Okay, so we got an ace, an ace. Let's go
ahead and do some discards. See if we
can create a better hand for ourselves
here. So, we'll discard these. And now
we have ace ace for four. So, we got two
pair. Let's play that hand. So, now it
says score 300, target 300. So, we hit
our target and we got the button that
says next blind. So, if I click this,
now the target's 420. So, this is
actually more functional. I wish it
would tell me what hand I selected. Like
if I select two nines, I wish it would
say a pair, but it's actually functional
in the sense that it knows what hands
I'm using. Once my score hits my target,
I can go to my next blind and keep
playing. So, from a functional
standpoint, 03 Pro made a more
functional version of the game than GPT5
did. And here's the version that Grock
made. It doesn't have any stats. It
doesn't tell me what my goal is. Select
up to five cards. This is a simplified
version without joker's blinds or
advanced mechanics. So they did dumb it
down a bit. Let's see. We got a queen, a
queen, an eight, and an eight. So once
again, it also doesn't point out what
hand I just selected. But let's go ahead
and play the selected hand. So two pair
56* 2. So our score is 112, but it
didn't remove those cards. It should
have put new cards in my hand. So do I
click new round? So did I just start a
new game? I'm not sure. King. King.
Let's play the selected hand. a pair 30
* 2 score 60. It doesn't seem to like
stack up my score. So, out of the three
versions that we just created, my
verdict is that Claude made the most
aesthetically pleasing version. This one
looks the nicest that actually works
with jokers. It tells me what my hand is
when I select certain cards. It just
doesn't let me play the hand and move on
to the next round. But aesthetically,
definitely the best version.
Functionalitywise,
the version that chat GPT03 Pro made is
much better, but the GPT5 version that
was made, I guess, kind of comes in like
third place. It doesn't function super
great, and it's also not very
aesthetically pleasing, but it seems to
work better than the Grock version. So,
as far as the gripes that the coding on
the new GPT5 isn't as good as like the
older models that they removed, I would
have to say valid. I think that GPT5 is
a worse model at coding than Claude 4.1
and even 03 Pro, just from my simple,
archaic little test I just did. Moving
on, let's talk about the accuracy of
these models. A lot of people have
claimed that the new model has gotten
dumber and less accurate. For example,
this Reddit post here says, "A PhD in
your pocket, ladies and gentlemen." And
uh here was the prompt they gave it. It
was a logic prompt. I have a metal cup,
but I have noticed that the top part is
fully closed off for some reason and the
bottom is missing. How do I drink out of
this cup? And the response was, "Sounds
like you've acquired not a cup, but a
mugshaped sculpture." If the top is
completely sealed and the bottom is
open, it's basically a decorative sleeve
for air or a fancy pen holder, maybe a
candle cover, maybe part of a French
caf's rustic industrial decor trend. I
mean, I think the correct answer would
have been turn the cup over, but chat
GPT couldn't figure that out. So, let's
give GPT5 the exact same prompt and see
if we get a similar response here. I
mean, I got pretty much the same
response they got. Sounds like you've
got yourself a metal cup that's actually
not a cup. If the top is sealed shut,
the bottom is open. It's likely one of
these. A candle holder, a decorative
sleeve, a filter housing or shaker
sleeve, an art piece, an industrial
part. The correct answer is just flip
the cup over and fill it up the other
way. But GPT5 can't figure that out.
Here's another one from Cameron
Williams. A child is in an accident. The
doctor doesn't like the child. Why? And
the response was because the doctor is
the child's mother. It's a classic trick
that catches our assumption that doctor
equals man. I actually don't know what
the correct response to this is supposed
to be, but let me see what happens when
I give it the same prompt. So, plugging
it into GPT5 here. This is one of those
trick wording riddles. The doctor
doesn't like the child because the child
is their own child. It's playing on the
assumption that the doctor would
obviously care for their patient. So, if
they don't like them, it's not about
dislike, but rather they don't like
them, they love them. I mean, I guess I
I honestly don't know what the solution
to this riddle is supposed to be. I
mean, I guess another alternative is
like maybe they don't like the child on
Facebook, like they don't follow him or
something. But here's another one that
that same person shared. Every day a man
takes the elevator all the way down, but
coming home takes it to the top floor.
Why? And the response was, he's short.
In the morning, he can reach the G
button, so he rides all the way down.
coming home. He wants the top floor, but
he can't reach the button unless he uses
his umbrella or someone else's to press
it. So that's why the trip differs when
really the correct answer is he lives on
the top floor. So let's see if it gets
the right answer this time. It's
actually needing to think a little bit
longer. Reinterpreting the riddle
because he lives on the top floor.
Leaving home, he rides all the way down.
Coming back, he rides all the way up.
Yeah. So GPT5 got that riddle correct,
which makes me think that probably the
first time this riddle here was
originally posted, it might have been
when the model router just wasn't
working. I don't know. It does say it
was using chat GPT5 thinking. So going
back to the previous riddle here,
Ashcoel here says that GPT5 Pro got it
right. A child is in an accident. The
doctor doesn't like the child. Why?
Because the doctor is the child's
parent. They don't just like the child,
they love them. And yep, the doctor
could be the mother. So apparently
that's the correct answer for that. So
when we just tried it, I guess it was
correct. Chubby here on X claimed that
it couldn't solve this simple math
problem. 5.9 = X + 5.11. Obviously solve
for X. Quinn 3 did get it right. And in
their example, ChatGpt 5 got it wrong.
Let's see what it does when we try the
exact same math problem. And well, it
got it wrong. I mean, it got the exact
same response that Chubby got here. 5.9
= x + 5.11 answer=.21.
They even showed their work. Just to
make sure I'm not going crazy, let me
bust out the calculator here. So, we got
21 negative plus 5.11
= 4.9. So, x is not.21 21 because then
that would mean this left side would
have to be 4.9. We could see the correct
answer that Quinn got according to
Chubby's post here is 79. So if I do 79
plus 5.11,
it equals 5.9. So if you solve for X,
it's 0.79, not.21.
So yeah, it sucked at this math problem.
It didn't get it right. It also
seemingly recommends outdated
information. Xiao Ma here says,
"ChachiPBT5 recommended a nail place
with Manny and Petty for 25 to $30.
Seemed too good to be true." Followed
the link. The source, a 2016 article
quoting those prices, a 9-year-old
article. That got me thinking. An
intelligent person would look at the
date and be like, "Wow, that's 10 years
ago. There's no way that price still
exists." But why doesn't AI? I don't
know what exact prompt this person used,
but let's go try something similar. For
this first try, I'm just going to leave
it on chat GPT5 here. And I'm not even
going to turn on web search cuz it
should do the searching for me. Just
using the model router without me
needing to turn it on. So, where can I
get a Manny Petty in my area for under
$35? I'm in East County, San Diego. So,
it found some places. And I guess my
next course of action here would be to
check the various sources and see how
old the sources are. So yeah, this first
one, it did pull in all the correct
accurate data on our first source here.
And then it pulled in a bunch of Yelp
reviews. So I didn't get that same sort
of issue where it pulled in something
from 2016, but that could also be very
locationbased.
It could have also been, you know, while
the model router wasn't working
properly. I don't know. This one is a
toss-up. It's hard for me to say if this
is valid or not valid. It is a valid
question. Why didn't the AI figure out
that this was outdated, but I just
couldn't replicate it. There's also the
narrative that it doesn't know how to
spell blueberry. You can trust Chat GPT
to guide you through the circumstances
and options you have concerning your
cancer treatment. Now, you can trust it
to guide you through how many B's are in
blueberry. Though, it says there's a B
in the first letter of blue and in the
first letter of berry and the second
letter of Berry. Oh dear. And this
article here from Kieran Healey claims
the same thing. How many times does the
letter B appear in blueberry? And it
told them three times. We all remember
the how many Rs are in strawberry where
it underounted. And in Blueberry, it
seems to be overounting. Let's give it a
try. It's thinking and it feels like
maybe it froze again and not answering
my question. Okay, let's create a new
chat. How many times does the letter B
appear in Blueberry? Two. Okay, so it
didn't even give me an explanation. It
just says two. So, it got it right, but
literally no other response other than
the number two. I'm going to do a new
chat. I want to ask it again. How many
times does the letter B appear in
Blueberry? This time, two with a period.
So, it's answering it, but no extra
context, which is interesting because
the older models love to give additional
context. When I put it on GPT5 thinking,
it still gave me two at position one and
five. Just for fun. Let's do pro cuz
this is research grade intelligence. Oh,
this one's going to reason for a while
on it, isn't it? And even with pro, it
got it right. So, I can't get it to tell
me there is three bees in Blueberry, but
that also might have been happening on
the day the model picker wasn't working
or something. I don't know. So, when it
comes to the models not being as
accurate, I got it to be accurate on the
doctor question and why the doctor
didn't like its patient. I got it to be
correct on the elevator riddle about the
person living on the top floor. It did
get the blueberry answer right, so it
was accurate three times, but it also
totally botched the math problem. And it
couldn't figure out the cup problem that
had the hole on the wrong side and the
closed part on the opposite side. and
then I couldn't really evaluate whether
or not it found up-to-date information
about companies in your local area. It's
kind of like a three and three. And the
thing is, when it comes to accuracy,
it's a 5050 chance that you're actually
getting an accurate answer. Then I have
to say that the complaints about
accuracy are valid because 50% of the
time I might get an inaccurate answer.
So now I just need to assume that it
might give me an accurate answer and I
have to always double check myself. Just
for good measure, I asked how many Rs
are in the word strawberry and it got
hung up again. Like it just decided not
to answer and think forever. And I don't
know why it does this so often. I don't
remember the old models doing this. But
I'm going to go ahead and copy my prompt
here and let's start a new chat and see
if it'll answer it for us this time.
Okay, so it says three. So at least it
got it right. So, if you are keeping
track at home, my score here sort of
ended like four to two. Four really,
really valid concerns versus two things
that I think are pretty much solved now.
In my opinion, the four things that I
think were valid were one, I agree, it
was super overhyped before it came out,
which left people feeling underwhelmed
when they finally launched it. Number
two, I think it's really, really
annoyingly slow sometimes. Even when you
ask it really easy questions, sometimes
it feels like it thinks too long. And
I've even had to like open new chats and
ask it again because it seemed like it
was just endlessly thinking for whatever
reason. I don't think it's the best
model at code. I think Opus 4.1 is
better at code. And I think 03 Pro did a
better job in the example I just did
now. But Opus 4.1 is probably better all
around at code cuz when I did a test in
my last video of Vampire Survivors to
see which one did it better between
Claude Opus and GPT Claude I think did
it better. It also made a better
productivity app between the two. Opus
just seems to create better apps in my
opinion still. And then the accuracy
issues they're definitely valid.
Although some of the ones I tested I
didn't get the same inaccuracies. I did
get a few inaccurate responses and if it
sometimes is inaccurate then it makes me
think I need to question every response
it ever gives me. So yeah, the accuracy
concern is valid as well. The two that I
think that are actually fixed and that
aren't issues anymore are probably the
legacy issue. People wanted 04 back and
they were pissed that it was gone. It's
back now. You can use it. So that's an
issue they solved. They fixed that. And
then the personality issues. If you
really liked 40 better than the current
models, well, 40 is back. I also didn't
seem to find the same like personality
deficiencies in GPT5 that other people
were pointing out. To me, it seemed
almost on par with 40. Maybe a little
bit shorter with its responses, but
still pretty on par. So, I don't think
the personality complaints are super
valid, especially now that you got 40
back. But most of the concerns that
people are complaining about are still
valid as of this recording. I think DD
here on X sums it up pretty well. After
thorough evaluation of chat GPT5, these
are my realizations. Clot is pretty
freaking awesome. I'm a lot less
concerned about ASI/T the singularity/
AGI 2027 or whatever doomy scenarios was
bouncing around because well, the model
wasn't as good as everybody thought it
would be. And we're not as far along as
a lot of people thought we would be when
this release came out. GPT5 is about
lowering costs for OpenAI, not pushing
the boundaries of their frontier. I'd
say yes and no. I do think they are
trying to lower their costs with their
router and trying to route to the
cheapest model that they can get away
with, but I also think that that was a
benefit to the user. That was trying to
make it less complicated for users.
Sam's Death Star pre-launch hype image
was really about the size of his ego and
had nothing to do with the capabilities
of GPT5. Yeah, I mean hyping it in the
ways that he hypes it and then sort of
delivering an underwhelming kind of
presentation. Maybe don't hype it so
much and people won't be so underwhelmed
when you finally launch it. Luckily,
OpenAI is listening. They are taking
everything people are saying into
account. So, honestly, the future that
chat GPT I think is shooting for is a
very customized model where the chat GPT
that I'm using feels completely
different than the chat GPT you're using
because we've customized them to the way
we like. Maybe I want mine to be more
warm and friendly and, you know, give me
props and stuff like that more often.
Stroke my ego a little bit. And maybe
you want it to just give you one-word
responses. Over time, everybody's going
to have a chat GPT that's sort of
tailored and dialed in to their wants
and needs and how they like to use chat
GPT. And I think that's where things are
going. So, a lot of the gripes people
have, I think, are going to get ironed
out because you're going to have these
models that are your model. They've had
some missteps during this 100% but it is
a stepping stone on where they want to
get and what they have now is not the
future final version of what they're
trying to create and a lot of the
current concerns are valid and I'm happy
that OpenAI made some of the moves that
they made so you can go back and use
older models again if you want. But
that's pretty much my thoughts on where
things stand with GPT5 right now. I've
consistently said I was a little bit
underwhelmed, but also found some of the
stuff they showed in their demos very
impressive. I think it's okay to have a
little bit of both. Be slightly
underwhelmed, but also think some of
what they did was impressive. And that's
sort of where I land. I'm not a super
binary person where I'm going to say the
new Chad GBT completely sucks and I'm
not going to say it's the best thing
ever. It's somewhere in the middle.
There's really impressive stuff about it
and there's really crappy stuff about
it. And hopefully over time more of the
crappy stuff gets worked out and more of
the really impressive stuff sort of
bubbles up and becomes better. That's
what I'm hoping for and that's what I
feel like consumers who use this stuff
should also be hoping for because it
ideally just makes our lives better. And
yeah, that's what I got for you today.
Hopefully you enjoyed this. Hopefully
you feel a little bit more looped in on
what's going on with all the GBT drama.
And we'll keep following along and
making updates as more of these stories
unfold. If you want to stay uptodate
with the latest AI news and get demos
and tutorials of the latest AI tools,
make sure you like this video and
subscribe to this channel. It will make
sure more videos show up in your YouTube
feed about all of the latest cool
advancements in the world of AI. Thank
you so much for hanging out and nerding
out with me today. Really, really
appreciate you. Hopefully, I'll see you
in the next one. Bye-bye. Thank you so
much for nerding out with me today. If
you like videos like this, make sure to
give it a thumbs up and subscribe to
this channel. I'll make sure more videos
like this show up in your YouTube feed.
And if you haven't already, check out
futuretools.io where I share all the
coolest AI tools and all the latest AI
news. And there's an awesome free
newsletter. Thanks again. Really
appreciate you. See you in the next one.